

■ ek8093@rit.edu | 🎓 emilykuang.github.io | 🖫 emilykuang | 🛅 emilykuang6

At the forefront of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Artificial Intelligence (AI), and User Experience (UX), my research focuses on designing and evaluating human-AI collaborative tools for improved usability and UX analysis. Honored with the 2023 Google PhD Fellowship in HCI, my work not only advances technology but also champions accessibility, focusing on inclusive computing education and assistive technology for diverse user groups.

Education

Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, US

PhD in Computing and Information Sciences

Aug 2020 - present

- Advised by Dr. Kristen Shinohara and Dr. Mingming Fan
- Participating in the AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (NRT) Program

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, ON, CA

Sept 2015 - Apr 2020

BASC IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

- · Capstone advised by Dr. John Zelek
- · Graduated on Dean's Honour List

Experience_

Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, US

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug 2020 - present

- Conduct HCI research on the human-centered design of Al-powered technologies, focusing on visual analytic tools and conversational assistants to support UX analysis
- Design, conduct, and analyze research studies employing a variety of methods including interviews, surveys, design probes, usability studies, and quantitative experiments
- Author technical papers for publication and develop dissemination plans

Meta, Reality Labs

Seattle, WA, US

UX RESEARCH INTERN

May 2023 - Aug 2023

- Designed and led a 20-participant interview study on VR headset user experiences, efficiently collaborating with research
- Actively contributed to project brainstorming workshops and internal product demos
- Effectively communicated findings to diverse product stakeholders, promoting a comprehensive understanding of user perspectives and needs

Meta, Reality Labs

Burlingame, CA, US

UX RESEARCH INTERN

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- Conducted literature reviews and authored reports on first-hand experiences to inform the design of Ray-ban | Meta smartglasses
- Designed and conducted a user study with 30 participants to investigate audio performance
- Presented results to >100 product stakeholders including researchers, engineers, and cross-functional partners; recommendations led to changes in product design

Uncharted Software Inc., ASKE-E Team

Toronto, ON, CA

RESEARCH INTERN

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Worked on the DARPA Automating Scientific Knowledge Extraction (ASKE) program
- Designed wireframes and implemented new features in the human-machine interface (HMI) of a visual analytics system for multi-scale graph analysis and knowledge discovery

Huawei Technologies Canada, Human-Machine Interaction (HMI) Lab

RESEARCH ENGINEER

Markham, ON, CA Jan - Aug 2019, May - Aug 2020

- Trained machine learning models for gesture recognition using Tensorflow
- Designed and conducted user experiments to explore novel interaction techniques on large screens using mid-air gesture input; presented at the Huawei Developer Conference 2019

University of Waterloo, Vision and Image Processing (VIP) Lab

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Waterloo, ON, CA May 2016 - Apr 2018

- Designed and 3D-printed a lens-free microscope and a smartphone spectrometer
- · Conducted testing with biological specimens to achieve optical resolution in the nm range

Publications

CONFERENCE PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

[C.12] Bridging the Literacy Gap for Adults: Understanding How Streamers Teach Adult Literacy on Livestreaming Platforms

SHIHAN FU, JIANHAO CHEN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 (To appear)

[C.11] Designing Unobtrusive Modulated Electrotactile Feedback on Fingertip Edge to Assist Blind and Low Vision (BLV) People in Comprehending Charts

CHUTIAN JIANG, YINAN FAN, JUNAN XIE, EMILY KUANG, KAIHAO ZHANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 (To appear, first two authors contributed equally)

[C.10] Exploring the Opportunity of Augmented Reality (AR) in Supporting Older Adults Explore and Learn Smartphone Applications

XIAOFU JIN, WAI TONG, XIAOYING WEI, XIAN WANG, EMILY KUANG, XIAOYU MO, HUAMIN QU, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 (To appear)

[C.9] Mapping Accessibility Assignments into Core Computer Science Topics: An Empirical Study with Interviews and Surveys of Instructors and Students

EMILY KUANG, SELAH BELLSCHEIDT, DI PHAM, KRISTEN SHINOHARA, CATHERINE M. BAKER, YASMINE N. ELGLALY Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 (To appear)

[C.8] Enhancing UX Evaluation Through Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants: Effects of Proactive Dialogue and Timing

EMILY KUANG, MINGHAO LI, MINGMING FAN, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 (To appear)

[C.7] Understanding Strategies and Challenges of Conducting Daily Data Analysis (DDA) Among Blind and Lowvision People

CHUTIAN JIANG, WENTAO LEI, EMILY KUANG, TENG HAN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility [Acceptance rate: 30.2%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3597638.3608423

[C.6] Enhancing Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience Using the T9 Keyboard on Small Touchscreen Devices EMILY KUANG, RUIHUAN CHEN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581105

[C.5] Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants for UX Evaluation: Questions and How to Ask them (Voice vs. Text)

EMILY KUANG, EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581247

[C.4] Bridging the Generational Gap: Exploring How Virtual Reality Supports Remote Communication Between Grandparents and Grandchildren

XIAOYING WEI, YIZHENG GU, EMILY KUANG, XIAN WANG, BEIYAN CAO, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023

DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581405

[C.3] "Merging Results Is No Easy Task": An International Survey Study of Collaborative Data Analysis Practices Among UX Practitioners

EMILY KUANG, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 24.7%], 2022 DOI: 10.1145/3491102.3517647

[C.2] "Too old to bank digitally?": A Survey of Banking Practices and Challenges Among Older Adults in China XIAOFU JIN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference [Acceptance rate: 27.7%], 2021 DOI: 10.1145/3461778.3462127

[C.1] Compensated lens-free light field spectroscopy

Ameneh Boroomand, Mohammad Shafiee, Linda Wand, Emily Kuang, Farnoud Kazemzadeh, Alexander Wong International Conference on Inverse Problems in Engineering, 2017

JOURNAL ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

[J.3] CoUX: Collaborative Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos for Digital Interfaces

EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 28.1 (2022) pp. 643–653. 2022

DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114822 (First two authors contributed equally)

[J.2] Compact, Field-Portable Lens-free Microscope using Superresolution Spatio-Spectral Light-field Fusion FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, EMILY KUANG, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016). 2016 DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.105

$\lceil J.1 \rceil$ Enhanced Smartphone Spectroscopy via High-throughput Computational Slit

EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016). 2016

DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.97

EXTENDED ABSTRACTS & WORKSHOP PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

[P.2] Crafting Human-AI Collaborative Analysis for User Experience Evaluation

EMILY KUANG

In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544549.3577042

[P.1] A Multi-scale Visual Analytics Approach for Exploring Biomedical Knowledge

Fahd Husain, Rosa Romero-Gómez, Emily Kuang, Dario Segura, Adam Carolli, Lai Chung Liu, Manfred Cheung, Yohann Paris

Proceedings of the Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC), 2021

DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2109.06828 (Best Paper Award)

Honors and Awards

RECEIVED DURING PHD

2023 Googl	Ph.D. Fellowshi	p in Human-Com	puter Interaction,	Google
-------------------	-----------------	----------------	--------------------	--------

- 2022 AWARE-AI NRT Seed Funding Award (\$1000 USD), RIT
- 2022 **Department Nomination for Microsoft Research Ph.D. Fellowship**, RIT
- 2021 **Best Paper Award**, Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC)
- 2020 Merit-based Ph.D. Scholarship, RIT

RECEIVED DURING UNDERGRADUATE

2018	Experience Award	l, Natural Sciences and	d Engineering Researc	h Council of Canada

- 2018 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2017 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2016 Undergraduate Student Research Award, NSERC
- 2015 **President's Scholarship of Distinction**, University of Waterloo

Invited Talks and Poster Presentations _____

Jan 2024	Invited panelist , AWARE-AI NRT Retreat: Session on Resume Building & Internships	Remote
Nov 2023	Invited speaker, Youth Professional Career Development Series	Remote
Apr 2023	Poster presenter, CHI Doctoral Consortium	Hamburg, Germany
Oct 2022	Poster presenter, RIT Artificial Intelligence Summit	Rochester, NY
Apr 2022	Poster presenter, CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women	New Orleans, LA

Teaching Experience _____

ISTE-798 Future Interactions

RIT

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan 2024 - present

• Collaborate with the course instructor to plan and organize course materials

Reviewer: Late Breaking Work, Chinese CHI 2021

· Mentor students and provide constructive feedback on assignments, projects, and research

GUEST LECTURES

Sept 2023	Human-AI Collaboration for UX Evaluation, PhD Research Colloquium (CISC896)	RIT
Apr 2023	Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience, Design For Accessibility (ISTE266)	RIT
Nov 2021	Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos, Visual Analytics (ISTE782)	RIT

Service

2021

SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION

2023	Associate Chair, Chinese CHI 2023	
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI'24	Special Recognition
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CSCW'23	
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, Frontiers in Computer Science	
2022	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI'23	Special Recognition
2022	Student Volunteer (In-person), CHI'22	
2021	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI'22	
2021	Student Volunteer (Virtual), VIS'21	

SERVICE TO THE UNIVERSITY

- 2023 PhD Student Representative, GRAD Open House
- 2023 Trainee Council Representative, AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship
- Project Judge, Genius Olympiad 2022

Additional Professional Experience _____

North Inc. (now acquired by Google)

COMPUTER VISION DEVELOPER

Kitchener, ON, CA

Apr 2018 - Aug 2018

• Designed algorithm to quantify image sharpness for multi-camera system assembly

Synaptive Medical Inc.

OPTICS ENGINEERING INTERN

Toronto, ON, CA Sept 2017- Dec 2017

• Investigated the stabilization of stereoscopic videos for a neurosurgical robot

St. Michael's Hospital

MEDICAL IMAGING RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Toronto, ON, CA

Jan 2017 - Apr 2017

• Worked on a video processing pipeline for non-invasive detection of diabetic foot ulcers

Media Coverage _____

10/16/2023 Two RIT students earn Google Ph.D. Fellowships for AI computing research, 10/13/2023 Google PhD Fellowship recipients,

RIT News Google Research